<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://torshepherd.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://torshepherd.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-01-14T18:04:05-05:00</updated><id>https://torshepherd.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Tor Shepherd</title><subtitle>Website of Tor Shepherd, MS in Robotics at the University of Michigan Ann Arbor. I love controls - optimization, classical linear feedback, etc.  Find my code, resume, and projects on this website.</subtitle><author><name>Tor Shepherd</name></author><entry><title type="html">Modeling Emergent Behavior in Ants (kind of)</title><link href="https://torshepherd.com/projects/2020/01/14/emergent-behavior.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Modeling Emergent Behavior in Ants (kind of)" /><published>2020-01-14T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-01-14T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://torshepherd.com/projects/2020/01/14/emergent-behavior</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://torshepherd.com/projects/2020/01/14/emergent-behavior.html">&lt;p&gt;As part of the course ‘Bio-Inspired Design’ from my undergrad, we were assigned a team project to make something that takes inspiration from something in nature. We chose ants for their emergent behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;emergent-behavior&quot;&gt;Emergent Behavior&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emergence takes place when the behavior of set of agents is significantly different than the behavior of each agent. This does not simply refer to intentional teamwork such as humans might do (coordinating, collaborating), but to situations where basic logic rules implemented in autonomous units can produce much more complex results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Examples of emergent behavior in ants include fire ants acting as a single material when huddled in a mass, leaf cutter ants forming&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was what we were interested in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;map-sharing&quot;&gt;Map Sharing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/emerge-gif.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Simulation running&quot; /&gt;
As agents navigate a 2d grid trying to find a goal, they move almost randomly, trying to expand their knowledge frontier about the map. When two agents are next to one another, their maps synchronize, becoming the union of each of their previous maps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The effect is that they can approximately delegate parts of the map for each to search, telling each other that their sector is clear when they happen to bump into each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;results&quot;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/emerge.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;Analysis&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project was completed during my undergrad; I had not learned much about dynamical systems, controls, or even just smarter search algorithms which could have made the experiment have far better performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the resultant behavior of increasing the number of agents does show that performance increased significantly more when map-sharing was enabled than without. Notice from each figure:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The 3-agent simulation is spread widely across number of solve steps taken, but clustered closely in number of interactions. The 9-agent simulation shows the opposite trend.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The 3-agent simulation has a much higher variance in solve steps than the 9-agent simulation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increasing the number of agents has diminishing returns, as at some point, the entire map gets explored relatively quickly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At low agent numbers, the units are more likely to find the goal by luck, increasing the variance in steps taken. Increasing agent numbers leads to more consistent solve steps due to emergent behavior, but also increases the variance in number of interactions due to crowding (higher likelihood of agents bumping into each other).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read the full report &lt;a href=&quot;/pdf/emergent_behavior_simulation.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and find all the necessary code on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/torshepherd/emerge&quot;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Tor Shepherd</name></author><summary type="html">As part of the course ‘Bio-Inspired Design’ from my undergrad, we were assigned a team project to make something that takes inspiration from something in nature. We chose ants for their emergent behavior.</summary></entry></feed>